[announcer] One, two. One, two, three, four.
♪ [music starting] ♪
If you enjoy James Brown music,
you're gonna have a good time tonight.
We are tonight celebrating Black Velvet
James Brown, Jr.'s 62nd birthday.
Whoo, 62!
So right about now, put your hands together,
because we got a young man
who's coming to the stage,
who's been on the David Letterman Show,
put your hands together and meet and greet
Black Velvet, James Brown, Jr!
[audience applause]
♪ [It's a Man's Man's Man's World playing] ♪
♪ It's a man's world. ♪
♪ But I would be nothing, nothing ... ♪
- [Charles] I've been playing James Brown
since I was 14 years old.
♪ [song ending] ♪
[audience applauding]
[female audience shouting]
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
But now I wanna do Charles Bradley.
♪ [music playing] ♪
My first album original
is coming out January 25th.
I've been struggling for over 42 years
trying to make it in the industry
and at age the of 62,
I'm just beginning to find my way through.
I never made enough money
to support myself in music
but I'm hoping that this album will
make a turning point for me,
that I can support myself in music.
Hey, man.
I'm gonna give you water, okay?
That's my bird.
Make me mad.
I get mad, I get away from it.
I go in the back room, close the door,
and let him scream all he wanna.
And I have my little stable place,
it's not what I want,
but thank God I got a roof over my head.
When I go in my little apartment
and lock my door,
I'm in peace.
But going into the projects,
going into the elevator,
getting in there,
that's where the trouble start.
You never know
what gonna happen in those things.
The guy downstairs,
his name is Alfred,
very good guy, don't bother nobody.
Church guy.
They shoot up his place.
He showed me all the holes
where they shoot up in the place.
I said, "Wow, man."
I said,
"Uh, I couldn't live on the first floor."
[Charles] When it get too
crazy at the projects,
I go to my Mom's house
and I sleep in her basement.
So I come here
and this is where I crash.
Until the next day,
I go take care of their errands,
take care of everything
to keep the roof over both our heads.
I like to roll a little of this
in a little ball.
Just put these in.
[Charles] Hey, how's that rice?
- Let me see?
Just a little bit more.
- I came from family of eight.
Um, main goal is watching over,
is my mom and do the best I can.
- It's my baby boy,
and I love him.
[Mom] He wash my clothes.
He clean this house.
Valentine's Day,
he bought me a box of candy.
As sweet as that candy is,
is how sweet my baby is.
- [Charles] I just making
her life peaceful
and
so, where she cannot worry about
the bills and everything.
I took that upon my shoulder
and I really,
I didn't know what I was getting myself into.
But now, I'm in it.
I won't change it.
So only thing I can do is try
make something to work
where I can make a decent income
where I can live and let live.
And that's all I, I can ask for life now.
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
♪ Round and round we go again.
♪ Where it stop, nobody knows.♪
♪ It's a cold, cold world. ♪
♪ How can we stop the changes ♪
♪ going on in America today?♪
♪ Ohhh, ohhh, ohhh ♪
♪ Go back. ♪
♪ Go back to the Golden Rule. ♪
♪ Oh. Ah. Uh. ♪
♪ Go back. ♪
♪ Go back to the Golden Rule. ♪
♪ Bring it all down. ♪
♪ [Music] ♪
- That's a song
from the new record, No Time For Dreaming.
Charles Bradley
and the Menahan Street Band.
I can't believe
you just came outta nowhere
as a virtual unknown to us.
[radio DJ] Have you recorded before?
- No.
And it's my first time really, coming out.
- I know you've been performing.
- Yes.
- As Black Velvet.
-[Charles] Yes.
- So now you're performing as-
as Charles Bradley?
- Yeah, yeah.
- [radio DJ] Well, you certainly have a great band
backing you here.
And of course,
with the folks over at Daptone,
you know,
what a great crew they are.
And you've seen
what's happened with Sharon Jones, who,- [Charles] Yes, yes.
you know, just like you,
went from complete obscurity to
who knows what kinda heights you could scale.
[radio DJ] So that's,
that's got to be an exciting moment for you?
- I think God just answered my prayer,
you know, it just like really,
I asked myself why it took so long,
but you can't question God
when he wanna do things.
So at my late age, it just started coming.
- [radio DJ] What's next?
I mean, are you thinking big?
- I'm thinking the sky's the limit.
- Congratulations to you on this great record.
No matter what happens with it,
it's a fine piece of work.
[radio DJ] Charles Bradley on WFUV.
♪ [Music] ♪
♪ This world going up in flames. ♪
♪ And nobody wanna take the blame. ♪
♪ Don't tell me how to live my life. ♪
♪ When you never felt the pain. ♪
♪ Ohhh. Ahhh. Ohhh ♪
♪Ohhh.♪
♪ Don't they see me cry? ♪
♪ Ohhh... ♪
♪ [music fading] ♪
- I don't know how many artists
have ever been 62 years old
and released their debut record.
He may be the first.
- The guy is just getting it,
getting it going, as far as I'm concerned.
-He's worked very hard for a long time.
And I'd hope that-
that enough people can hear him sing,
so that-
that he can make the kind of life for himself
that he wants and take care of his family.
♪ [music starting] ♪
♪ Uh. Yeah. ♪
♪ I'm talking to you girl. ♪
♪ Yeah. ♪
♪ Only you ... ♪
[Charles] I went to Gabe
'cause I thought that he knew what he was doing.
And I felt that he can give me a helping hand
where I can get out to the music industry.
All I knew how to do is get on stage and to perform.
- If you're into funk and soul music or Afrobeat and you live in New York,
Gabe Roth is the guy that you want behind the board.
This is the guy that you want pushing you in the direction,
because their records were phenomenal.
-I just started making the kind of records that I like listening to.
I think a lot of those soul records have a
certain sincerity to 'em that I always liked.
One morning, and I think it was pretty early,
it was like nine or ten in the morning,
I get a knock on my door and it was Charles.
[Gabe] And he said, I heard you were looking for singers.
Well, I heard you were looking for me.
I had no idea what he was talking about.
So, he shows me this video tape of him singing these James Brown songs.
And he sounds great, you know?
- Gabe Roth from Daptone Records brought him down to a rehearsal
in Staten Island that we were having.
And Gabe wanted us to record with a singer.
So Charles was a singer that they had yet to find a band
with on Daptone
but they had -- Charleshad captured their attention.
- I just figured, you know, see how Charles works with them, you know?
♪ Stop. ♪
♪ Stop it, baby. ♪
♪ Ohhh. ♪
♪ I'm feeling awful, baby. ♪
♪ And I'm locked up in cage ..." ♪
- I played with Tommy's, ah, band that he had over-over at Staten Island.
I just went over there one day and they was rehearsing.
They was jamming and they were sitting, telling me,
"Hey man, sing on this, sing on this,sing on this."
And I mean, I'm liking the music, I never -- the lyrics were just
popping in my head.
- So, that all worked out well. And we recorded those songs
with Bradley at Daptone and, uh, they were good songs
but they just didn't take off.
And then we kinda went in different directions.
- Two years went by and I was, um,doing James Brown in small clubs.
And then I got a call to come round, do a show with Sharon Jones.
- So we rehearsed, we played the show, great.
Me and Charles see each other for the first time in a couple years,
and, uh, you know, we catch up a little bit and I say, "Hey Charles, you know,
I'm working on some music, so how about you come over one night
and we give it a shot."
And he said, "Yeah Tommy, of course, you know."
We magically recorded two songs in one night.
One which was, The World's Going Up in Flames,
and one which was, In You, I Found a Love.
And Charles was right here and I was right here, pressing record,
and we, you know, we wrote it together, and, uh, and that was it.
I mean the music was laid down but he was just coming out
with lyrics off the cuff, and I was just, uh, putting it in the right place.
♪ [music starting] ♪
Okay, we haven't played so many shows with Charles up to this point.
We played a couple live performances,I think for -- for Charles is, you know,
he's -- he just wants -- he wants to get across, and he wants to,
uh, you know, he wants to reach every single person in the audience.
So, what you -- what we rehearse and what goes down on stage
is two different things.
I mean, the band's gonna be tight,and the only thing we try to rehearse
with Charles is to let Charles lead the band.
♪ [band rehearsing] ♪
- Bam, bam, bam, bam.
- Three, four.
♪ [Band practicing] ♪
♪ In you, I found love. ♪
♪ That makes me feel so real. ♪
♪ Oh, baby. ♪
♪ Sometimes, when I'm sleeping at night, ♪
♪ I wake up and you're nowhere to be found. ♪
♪ You said you loved me and you'll always be around. ♪
♪ In you, I thought I ... ♪
- The new music, for once, is me.
It's things that I have experienced and I have went through, heartaches
and pains.
♪ I don't want to be a fool no more. ♪
♪ [music stopping] ♪
- Yeah, Bradley. You waited twice for the horns.
- You told me that...
- Yes, that's perfect.
[band applauding]
- I'd like to say goodnight.
We can always do this sometime.
It was - it was a real party, Tommy
- All right, man and--
- that was excellent.
- Tommy again, thank you.
You know I love you.
Thank you bro.
Bye.
I ain't closed the door.
[Car passing by]
[Mom] Nine and a half.
[Charles] Mother, come on now.
You, you said nine, you said eight, eight and a half.
I get eight.
Now you want nine, you want nine and a half.
What's wrong with this shoes, right there?
Mother, you're gonna drive me crazy.
[shuffling sounds]
[Charles] Oh, Jesus.
It's hard sometime.
It's very hard, 'cause I can, like, everything now is really
depending on me.
But if I put her in a home, she would die.
And I know that.
[Mom] I had a stroke one time.
And I had many heart attacks.
[Sales Clerk] Enjoy the rest of your day.
[Mom] But that heart attack come when my-my step-daddy died
and my grandmother died,and, uh, when, when my husband
died.
[Charles] She said, "Son, let me spend my last days in the house."
I said, "Okay, mom, I'll do that."
But she don't know I have no life.
My life is her.
For me to be with someone, I don't even know how to do it.
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
- When Charles' mother first left Florida to go to New York,
Charles was only eight months of age,eight months old.
And she stayed away so long thatwhen she came back for the first time
he didn't recognize her, he didn't know she was his mother.
He thought that his grandmother, really was his mother.
- I came to New York to better myself for all of us.
Me and my husband were separated,and I wanted to better myself, and I did.
I bought the home, 843 Willoughby Avenue.
Uh-huh.
- She abandoned, actually in a way,her children to follow a man
who had a wife that she was very crazy about.
Otherwise, she probably never would have gone to New York.
[Charles] Oh, I was about the age of seven to eight years old when I was .
Our mother, when she came out, she-she told my grandmother,
"I want him to to come back and live with me."
My grandmother said, "No, let them stay here 'cause they are better off.
They'll get a better education if they stay down here with me."
So my mother says, "No."
So my grandmother said, "No, you're not taking them."
So, my mother stole us.
- They were mine.
So I figured, I got 'em. I mean, I created 'em.
So, then I'm gonna bring all my creations back to New York with me.
Mm-hm.
That's what I did.
- I really hate to say this, but I think, at that time it was hard to find jobs,
so there was only one way is you have some kind of dependents
that you can get some welfare.
And I feel like that's what she was doing
to get the welfare by having those kid there.
- During his infancy, now he was the, the favorite child.
He received all the, the-the loving and caring from his older brothers and sisters
and his grandmother and his uncles and all of us,
because he was the baby.
- Uh, when Charles went to New York, I think that's when he lost all of that.
- I was living with my Mom,
and I was afraid that she was gonna hurt me, so I left.
We couldn't see eye to eye.
See, I was getting blamed for everything.
So I was very bitter.
And it seemed like everything was rationed to us,
and I was in a basement worser than this one.
You know, it was just sand basement, it was no concrete basement.
Fifteen watt bulb light.
And I said "No, I can't take this."
I said, "I don't want it, I'm going."
So I left.
[Sound of a subway train passing]
I was fourteen years old.
My home was the subway train.
That's where I'd go to keep warm.
I'd get on the subway train some nights, or winter nights, cold.
Riding the A train back up and down.
The police, pop, pop, pop, hit the darn thing real hard
and say, "Kids, you need to get off."
I'd go across the, the platform, getanother train going back. I sleep.
Get me a little corner and get astick and knock the thing real hard.
It penetrate through my head.
He said, "Kids, get up. Kids, get up."
So, I just keep going different routes toget a night's sleep before daylight come.
And I see for myself, what's going down, because everybody back in those days
was getting high, using the hard drugs.
I'd watch them holding upwhile they're shooting up
and they try to give it to me,
I got scared and I was afraid of needles.
I said, "No, no, no, no."
So that's when I headed to Jobs Corps.
And I tried to get my mother to sign me to go to Job Corps.
And she was mad with me, she wouldn't sign.
So I got my sister to forge her name.
And, um, I learned to cook.
I cooked for two years.
I was a cook trainee up in Bar Harbor, Maine.
And that's when I really started doing James Brown on the Job Corps.
But they said, "Man, you see that new guy that came in?
He looks just like that guy they call, James Brown."
And they got me fired up one day, they gave me some gin.
In the Job Corp, you were sneaky, you were supposed to sneak it in there.
They gave me some gin, got me really high,
and they gave me the microphone and they say, "Sing."
And I went crazy.
So then they told me to go -- they took me to a girls' Job Corps
center to perform.
I said, "How many peoples it's gonna be?"
They said twenty or thirty peoples.
I said, "Okay."
And they called me on stage.
And I look out that stage.
And I saw all those peoples, and I froze.
I said,
"Uh-uh, I ain't going out there. Not me, not me"
So, this guy named Moody came behind me and gave me a push.
I see all the peoples was happy.
They love me.
They love me giving them my heart.
And I said, "Wow, this where I want to be at."
And I never stopped.
Our plans was when we got out of Job Corps
we was gonna get together and continue the music.
My band got drafted into the Vietnam War.
And, um, they went on to war and I went,completed my training at Job Corps.
[keys jingling]
[female voice humming]
- I wanna taste it when you open, uh, the beer that is a pumpkin.
- [Tommy] Oh, yeah.
- I gotta taste that.
- We can open it now.
- A pumpkin beer. I never heard of pumpkin beer.
- [Tommy] Oh, yeah. We can drink some of that.
- I sure wanna taste that.
[Charles] Okay.
-Oh my God, this is delicious.
-[Charles] That's, uh, pumpkin?
- Seriously, this is unbelievable.
-[Charles] That's a pumpkin?
-[Tommy] Yo!
-That's the pumpkin?
-[Tommy] It is like effect in some people
You like it, now?
-[Charles] No.-[Tommy] You don't like it?
-I just don't like it.
- I think it's delicious.
- I'm gonna taste the pumpkin in there.
-Working with Charles Bradley, as opposed to working with
Sharon or Lee or somebody,
the other singers from New Yorkthat I've so often worked with,
you know, Charles has got the craziest stories.
Craziest stories.
So, you know as a songwriter, I just sit around with him,
and, and I hear Charles tell these stories and you're just like,
you know, we gotta write a song about that, man.
So usually before we do the vocals on the track,
[Tommy] I'll play Charles' song and just ask him if he likes it, first of all.
Then, I'll sing him my ideas, you know, to tell him how I think it should go.
And not that he disregards my ideas,but he's just got his own ideas
and he just instantly starts expressing them.
He'll just start singing, and then we'll kind of stop
and just get away from it for a second and just talk.
And you just start--
you talk with Charles long enough and a story comes out about something.
[Tommy]That without me asking him, he'll start singing about what we just-
what we just spoke about.
And then I'll grab a pencil and paper,and let him kind of freestyle
over the track, over and over again.
And then we'll go back and that will become a song slowly, you know,
over the course of a couple of hours.
But, um, it's his stories that I'm always trying to translate into song, you know.
♪ [music] ♪
-[Charles] I went to California in 1977, searching for my dreams, music.
I was bouncing into different bands,
like they'll say, "Man, we'll pay you $400to do this tonight, the show tonight.
And this guy paid this, paid me to do this tonight.
That's how I was doing out there.
And at that time, I don't know why, I got sick.
I called my Mom, and she says,"Son, come on back home."
Mom is getting old and then, she been through a lot.
And I, it's not for me to crucify her for what she did in her life.
So I came back to New York in '94.
I was sick as a dog, I was close to death.
They took me to Woodhull Hospital.
[Charles] I'm allergic to penicillin and they was feeding me penicillin.
And my body had shut down.
I had gave up totally.
Then my brother Joseph, he came, um, he came to the hospital to see me.
And he reached over and he kissed me.
He said, "Charles, no, no."
He whispered in my ear.
He said, "Bro, if you don't want to livefor yourself, please live for me."
He said, "Charles, I love you."
"You're my heart."
I said, I said, "Joe, I'll fight. I'll fight."
♪ [piano music playing] ♪
My brother just told me he said, "Charles,now do something that you wanna do."
"Follow your dreams."
"You love music, do it."
And I said, "Joe, I'd like to be something like you."
He said, "No brother, you can't be me."
"Don't ever want to be me. Be you."
- [Mom] Oh, that was his buddy.
He Joe. He was crazy about Charles.
He told Charles, "Whatever you do, do it good brother, and stick with it."
"Don't let nobody talk you out of it."
He told that before he died.
He said, "Don't nobody talk you out of it."
♪ [piano music continues to play] ♪
-[Charles] He said, "'Cause I can't do it, like you do it."
'Cause I remember when I was a kid when I was in Florida.
Joseph was going to piano schooland how I learned these little things,
I'm playing the piano, by watching him.
He never learned about his -- tuned it myself.
He said, "Follow your dreams and your music."
And he said, "Take one of these rooms in this house and fix it up
as your room and have people come out here for rehearsal."
And that's what I did.
Joe was like a father and a brother.
He was a beautiful brother.
[slicing/chopping sound]
- [Mom] So, where the fruits at?
[cooking/frying sound]
-[Charles] Is that enough?
-[female voice] A Little bit more.
- [Tutor] Yeah, sit down, Charles and eat.
- [Charles] I can make us some breakfast.
- I'm not hungry, but you eat.
And then we'll startslowly talking about what you did.
- Okay I'm gonna leave this right here for you.
- That's fine.
I'm tutoring Charles.
I would say he's probably at like a kindergarten or first grade
reading level and reading comprehension level.
- Other writers interested in my story.
- Okay, so you sounded it out.
Did you understand everything that you read?
- Um, yes and no.
-Yes and no.
- Charles?
- Hm?
- The lunch was delicious.
- Thank you, Momma.
- I think his number one goal is for him to be able to write his lyrics
down fast when they're coming into his head,
because he's got a lot of words up there that he wants to get on paper,
but he doesn't really know how to do it.
- You didn't spell, An it right.-Okay.
- Oh, two N's?
- Just one N. No, D.
- Oh, N.
- 'Cause AND is like when you put two things together like...
- Right, okay.
- Fish AND chips.
- Okay. I'll miss you.
- Bye Charles. I'll see you next week.
Thank you.
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
-[Barber] Come on in.
- [young boss] You got it? Yo! You could read it later. Wrap it up.
- No. Get the fuck outta here-Get started.
[young boss] You know I own you. You know I'm the boss.
- [Laughing] I bet you wish you was.
- Thank you, Mr. Brown.
- Charles used to wear his James Brown wig all the time, right?
All the time.
And as the record close to a near, it's like, "Charles you know,
you got to present yourself as Charles Bradley."
And he had a hard time.
I mean, he wanted to come out with the cape and the James Brown thing.
And just be that.
'Cause that's what he's used to getting up on stage and doing.
And we did not want that, you know.
And we just wanted Charles to be Charles.
And it took a lot of convincing for Charles to do that.
[small motorized tools working][sounds of traffic]
- Charles has a record coming out January 25th.
So, now starts the promotion leading up to the record coming out.
- [Charles] I'm going on tour with Sharon Jones to open up for her.
Sharon Jones is giving me a chanceto expose some of my music,
to let the world know who Charles Bradley is.
- It's real exciting for us as a label to be able to present these kind of
package deal, packages and Charles is the perfect guy to add
to any of the shows and get his name out on the heels of so many other bands that
have had success up to now.
- If we go some place and we are ableto have a thousand people come down
to see Sharon, to be able to put him in front of that audience is...
is a huge head start.
So far you know, the Sharon Jonesand Dap-Kings has been
our most prolific artists, and our most successful artists.
Artists, been around the longest,toured the most, and by far sold,
you know, ten times as many records.
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
- Didn't put out a proper show in about a year or so, you know,
to also put that in context,
he hasn't played a lot of gigs as Charles Bradley.
- Working with Bradley live is a little stressful,
because he can kind of go off in a song anytime.
- [Charles] America. We gotta make this room, a better place.
Come on, bring it all in.
♪ No time for dreaming ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming.♪
♪ Gotta get on up.♪
♪ [back-up singers] Get up ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing, oooooh... ♪
♪ No time for dreaming. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming.♪
♪ Gotta get on up, ♪
[back-up singers] Get up. ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing. ♪
♪[back-up singers] Do your thing. ♪
♪ Sleep while your sleeping. ♪
♪ Tired of slowly creeping. ♪
♪ Wake up!♪
♪ Before it's too late. ♪
♪ Try a little harder! ♪
♪ Stop wasting over yonder. ♪
♪ Wake up! ♪
♪ You'll get your break. ♪
♪ Huh! ♪
♪ No time for dreaming. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming. ♪
♪ Gotta get on up. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Get up! ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Ohhh...♪
♪ No time for dreaming. ♪
♪[back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming. ♪
♪ Gotta get on up. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Get up. ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing ♪
♪ [back-up singers] And do your thing. ♪
♪ Hey...♪
♪ [instrumental music playing] ♪
♪ Gotta ♪
♪ give ♪
♪ Yeah ♪
♪ No time for dreaming. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming. ♪
♪ Gotta get on up. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Get up. ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Ohhh...♪
♪ Huh! No time for dreaming. ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Dreaming, dreaming. ♪
♪ Gotta get on up ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Get up. ♪
♪ Gotta do your thing ♪
♪ [back-up singers] Do your thing. ♪
♪ No time for dreaming.♪
♪ You got to get on up ♪
♪ And do your thing. ♪
♪ [music fading] ♪
[audience applauding]
- [audience member] I love you.
- I love you, too. I love you, too.
-[audience member] love you, Charles.
-[Charles] I love you, too
[audience cheering/applauding]
- put your hands together and give it for Charles Bradley.
Show some love for Mr. Charles Bradley.
- Okay. Your smarter. Your smarter.
- It was better than last night,wasn't it?
- Yes, it was.
-[Tommy] It was better.-[Charles] Killed it
- So we won.
- It was.
- Just how long?
- I know I made a few mistakes tonight.
But I'm getting better and I feel it.
The audience didn't see it, but I know it.
And Tom, he know about it.
So, the last one I was good on.
And there's something I'm wonderingwhen I made a mistake on,
but I'm get better on it.And I promise you that.
- We can't believe that they didn't put you on more.
We wanted more of you.
Why didn't you come back on in the end?
Tell her.
[Charles mumbling]
- I don't care, we want more.
More of Chuckie.
- Thank you, my man.
Thank you for that.
You, you got the juices flowing for all of us.
Thank you.
- You just blew the roof off the place.
- Unbelievable. You're gonna be like huge, man.
- I don't understand what people mean about, "divas," you know,
'cause that, "diva" word can be -- sometimes can be wrong.
- No, but it's right for you.
- Diva means, you know, you just...-It all depends.
- Yeah.
- But it's coming from love, you gotta consider the source.
-This one is yours.
- "Consider the source."
-You have a good week.
- You didn't say, "To Charles." You didn't say, "To Charles."
-"Charles," how do you spell "Bradley?"
- Bradley, B-R-A-D-L-E-Y.
- ...L- E-Y.
- Cool. Now I got it.
- You got the sparks.
- I love you, Sharon.
- I love you, too.
- You, you have found a real friend in me and I wish the best for you.
- I wish the best for you, best for us.
- If I don't, if I don't see you at the top, I will see you in heaven.
- Oh, you're gonna see me, you'll see me on the top
and you're gonna see me in heaven.
You'll see me while I'll be down here too.
- I love you, Sharon.
- Love you too, Charles.
[Instrumental music playing]
-Poughkeepsie
- I'm gonna stop by and visit some old friends I haven't seen in many years.
[doorbell chime]
[door opening][people greeting each other with laughter]
-[Charles] I said, "God, I hope they're still here."
- Yeah, we're still here, Bro.
- [Charles] Wow, this house smells good!
-What's going on, buddy? How are you feeling?
- It's been years. Look at you.
- Oh, yeah. You look well, man.
- God, you look good too.
Is that Jackie coming down?
Ah! Look at Jackie!
How you doing?
I know this guy --
I know Ernie Washington since 1968.
- You know what, she was looking for now?
-[Charles] Um?
-You remember when you used to wear a cape?
- [Ernie] You were singing one of James Brown's songs,
and you'd throw that cape off.-[Charles] Oh, my God.
And I don't know if one of us went and picked the cape up
and lay it back on your shoulder or what.
- Yes, I remember that.
- Yeah.
- That's right.
You never would know, you went that far, huh?
- God. You know, I thank God I didn't, I didn't give up.
- Thank God.
- Let me speak to Tom.
Tell Tom that to put Mr. and Mrs. Washington on the guest list.
I found my friends.
They are totally my family.
We keep in touch, I mean, we goaway for so far long but eventually,
I'm gonna find them back.
- That's right.
- You know that, Jackie.
- Yeah, we've been friends for a long, long time.
- Yes, yes, God yes.
I get goosebumps even thinking about that.
I'll see you guys, I'll see you tonight.
- [Ernie] Take care, and I'll see you tonight.
- All right, bye.
Oh my God, that's memory lane.
On South Road,
I was standing in a house over there and we had a heavy snowstorm.
I called in sick.
I didn't wanna go in because I wasn't able to go through all that snow.
So he said, "Well, you call in sick again,you don't come in,
don't bother coming in no more."
And I said, well I don't wanna lose my job,
I got my apartment, got bills, gotta pay rent.
So I got out and I got on the road and started hitchhiking.
Hitchhiking, hitchhiking.
Then all of a sudden, I saw this guy stop.
Picked me up, got in the car.
After he drove about a mile or two miles and there was a StateTrooper
on the side behind him. And put the siren on and pulled him aside.
One of them came up to me and said, "Can I see your identification?"
Well, who's the guy next to you?
I said, "Now that's not my information to give you,
you have to get that information from him."
And so he grabbed me, called me a, "Wise Nigger."
And he grabbed me and throwed me against the car,
put the handcuffs on me.
He said, "I'd take you to the woods and bust your brains out.
When I ask you a question, don't act wise with me."
And I stayed there and then his partner came over and said, "Hey man."
Took him to the side, said something to him.
And then his partner, he kind of apologized to me.
Took the handcuffs off me and told me get in the car and go ahead.
And I left.
And I went into this little pizza shop.
Tiny pizza shop.
I was sitting down, I said, "God, I can't take this much."
"I'm at the end of my rope."
I was trying to think of a way to get outthis body without--if I can do it fast
without hurting and make sureI don't make a mistake and,
and live only to be suffering.
I said, I know a bus--if a truck hit me I know I'm gone, a car hit me I may live.
And I was trying to get, to build the nerve to do it.
And then all a sudden, this guy came in and he put some money in the jukebox
and he played this one song, Take It to the Limit One More Time.
Seemed to me that was God talking to me,
I was at the end of my rope.When I heard that song, I started crying.
And even the guy in the pizza shop said,
"It's all right, young man. It's all right."
And I got up and walked out and I went on the road.
♪ [music starting to play] ♪
♪ Ai-ai...♪
♪ Loving you baby ♪
♪ Oh, I can't get enough of you baby ♪
♪ Can't get enough of you ♪
♪ I was crying when I felt your love ♪
♪ This time I know it's for real, baby. ♪
♪ I... ♪
♪ [instrumental music playing] ♪
♪ Bring it down, fellas. ♪
Ladies and gentlemen, may ever who you are.
I live here about, I came here about--Poughkeepsie, about 1968.
And I lived here for 9 years.
You know, this is like home to me.
So, I'm giving you my love.
You know, bring it down a little somethin' fellas.
And I work in a little townthey call .
I worked in a little center, I was cook for 3500 peoples a day.
There's a friend in here, two friends that I know that,
that when I came here they was with me.
And his name is Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Washington.
Ernest Washington, I can't see you now, where you at?
But, thank you brother for the ride.
Thank you, Jackie.
Thank you for being my friend through the years.
And all of you out there.
♪ I love you.♪
♪ Yeah... ♪
♪ Would you see it? ♪
♪ Ohhh...♪
♪ Ooo....♪
Thank you, Ladies and Gentlemen, I love you.
- I saw you on YouTube, too.
That's how I knew the greatness of Charles Bradley.
- Thank you so much.
It was a great night.
- It really was.
- And you made it extra special.
- It's special, very special.
Thank you so much.
- God bless you.
- Thank you.
- That is our nephew, Cain.
- Thank you for coming for coming to Poughkeepsie.
You really blessed Poughkeepsie tonight.
- Thank you.
- Take care.
- Thanks for coming backfor one night.
- I got a touchy moment, one moment.
When I got down and started talking to some peoples.
Got touching.
So I said, Leave it alone, Charles.It's getting too deep now."
"Get off it."
I got back up 'cause it started getting touchy.
But that was the beautiful thing about you see, Ernest Washington and Jackie.
Oh, man.
Wow, this the first time they really saw me in many years.
[police siren wailing]
- [Charles] This is the house my brother was killed in.
That's why I don't like tocome on this block no more.
- He came downstairs and, uh, he saw me crying.
He said, "Mom what's wrong?"
I said, "Just go next door."
"Charles, your brother is dead."
He said, "No, Mama, can't be."
I said, "Yes, he is."
So there was probably a whole block was
filled with policemans with rifles and guns.
I look out the window, and I see all this polices,
and the firetrucks, ambulance outside.
So I came outside and I said, I just gotta go to see this myself.
'Cause I saw this thing says Morgue,and when it says Morgue, what I did,
I just, um, came out to go to my brother's house
and the detective wouldn't let me in there.
I told him that's my brother and you cannot stop me.
So I pushed my way in.
But I wish to God that I would've never would've did it.
- And they had the boy in the back of the car.
I said,"Give me your gun, Mr. Policeman."
I, I said, "I'll blow his damn brains out right through."
He said "I can't do that."
I said, "Good thing you can't because I'll put every damn bullet in his head."
He robbed my son and got his money.
I said, "I'll kill his ass."
And I meant it, too. Yes, sir.
I love my baby.
Mm-hm.
Sleep on, son. Take your rest.
God love you, but Momma.
I mean, Momma love you, but Godloves you best and give you eternal rest.
One day I will meet you on the throne.
Yes. Yes I will, son.
- I think, uh, Charles depended on Joseph just like, eh, mother depended on him.
Charles, uh, nearly went out of his mind when Joseph got killed.
I mean, for awhile they say he was gonna go crazy about it.
- [Charles] And I really like to find the truth of why he got killed.
He was too young.
He was 48 years old.
♪ [music playing] ♪
-[Tommy] There's a mic for you right here.
Do you just wanna try that one or do you wanna play something else?
-Yeah, we can come back...
You always, you go like that.
- [Tommy] You wanna do Heartaches and Pain?
♪ [Band starts playing] ♪
- Heartaches and Pain is by far the deepest song
on the Charles Bradley record.
and, uh, it was probably, uh, the third song that we had written together.
Charles tells me the story about hisbrother, and Charles says to me,
"I want to write a song about my brother Joseph."
I said, "Okay, I will help you do it." You know, as a friend.
And, ah, I said, "You know that song
you've been playing on the piano your whole life?
That's gonna be the music to the song.
Brought Charles in and added a couple things to his piano thing,
a couple chord progressions, whatever.
And, "Hey, Charles, this is the song for your brother."
And you know, he did his thing and hestarted screaming, running around,
"This is beautiful, this is beautiful. Oh, my God, oh my God."
And then we started working on it and it was hard, man. It was really hard.
That is a very personal, deep, deep, dark,haunting story about Charles' brother,
an older brother that, that he admired and loved,
that needed to tell.
♪ [Charles Bradley singing] ♪
- So the mortgage is hard on me,and I don't think it's fair to me.
Never missed a payment, 'cause they told me if I miss a payment,
they gonna up to 18% on my interest rate.
I've been trying to get it remortaged, remortgaged.
They tell me I don't make enough money.
I said, "Well, how I don't make enough money
and I'm paying all this mortgage, highmortgage I'm going out?"
'Cause I going out to earn pennies, every little penny, and keep this going.
- When Joseph got killed
and Charles went on, took on full theduty of taking care of what mother needs,
'cause none of 'em wanted to do it,
Charles is giving a lot of his personal money,
he puts it into the house to help her to stay there.
- He's in the process, I would say, almostbuying this darn house for his mother.
And-and his older sibling that lives there in the house.
Don't want him there.
And so he is largely responsible fortaking care of all of my sisters affairs.
♪ [Cell phone ringtone] ♪
- Hello.
- Yes?
- Oh, how, how you doing, Paul?
She's, if I, if she don't be able to do, be able to do the learn, the remodel,
refinance the house,then she will have to wait
for two months til income tax come.
Income tax coming, she would like me to give up my apartment,
but I don't want to give up my apartment, you know.
And then I'd have to move over to my mama's house.
Yeah, cause like this apartment that I was talking about,
is the only place I have to run to whenever I get depressed
and there's only pieces of me in here.
But whatever you decide is 'cause I know you're trying to help me.
and I appreciate that.
All right, Paul.
Thank you, Paul.
Okay.
What's left for me to do?
It's my life.
Take my life away.
Sometimes I do ask God just call me home.
Because everyday I get out and Ifight and fight to keep the honesty,
the decency of a human being walking the planet and loving
everybody as God asks you to love everybody.
But today, they look it as a weakness,I think.
How much more can one give before they find love on the planet?
How much more can you give?
I say, "Father, whatever the time or the hour you want me,
I'm ready to go."
That's the way I feel about life.
And before I leave this worldI said I let the world know
they can't change me.
I don't give a dog about what you give me,
ain't no money on this earth can take love that I have for God in my heart.
I love everybody.
I never do nobody no harm.
All I try to do is walk my straight life.
♪ [music starts playing] ♪
♪ Why is it so hard? ♪
♪ To make it in America.♪
♪ So I said to myself, ♪
♪ I, I gotta move away from here.♪
- Me and Homer were traveling in Europewith Sharon Jones and the Dap-Kings.
And we had hung out one night and met some girls in Paris.
So these girls were just like,
"Hey, you know, is Sharon Jones as big in America as she is in France?"
And you know, we're just like, no, no.
Nobody knows about Sharon Jones.
This is years ago, no one knows about Sharon Jones in America.
It's like we play around Brooklyn, and we play in small clubs,
but at the time, we were playing like theaters in Paris and such and
it was just a bigger thing in Europe.
So that led to us just kind of writing this little tune that night called:
Why Is It So Hard To Make It In America?
The second that Charles sang, Why Is It So Hard To Make It In America?
the song's meaning completely changed.
♪ [music continues to play] ♪
♪ Why is so hard to make it in America?♪
♪ I try ♪
♪ So hard, now, to make it in America. ♪
♪ Why?♪
♪ Tell me. ♪
♪ We gotta make a change in America. ♪
♪Help me somebody.♪
♪ Ohhh...♪
♪[music ends]♪
- Come here.
-Come here.
Come on.
Come here, Nicky.
You don't want to come now, okay.
You don't want to. I'll respect you're wishes.
Okay, I'll leave you alone.
You know, I had him ever since, since I was living in San Francisco.
I went to, um, a bird show.
I wasn't looking to buy a bird,'cause when I was a kid
I had me a pet chicken and that was my pet.
And I raised it from a little billy, from a little biddy it was yellow
and he turned to be a beautiful hen.
And he used to sleep with me and he was a beautiful hen.
Then one day, I had him about at least two years.
And my aunt came over one day,I came out my chicken would always be,
at the front of the driveway lookingfor me, for me to grab him.
And he wasn't there that day.
And I said, "Where's my chicken?"
Nobody know my chicken at.
Aunt Lily, "Where my chicken?"
She said, "Boy these chickens are so tame."
I said, "Where my chicken?"
She said, "Well, I'm roasting this chicken in the oven."
And I look in the oven, that was my chicken.
And I took that chicken out.
I dug a hole and buried him in the hole and put a cross on it.
And I started crying.
My grandmother came,and she said,
"Lily, that's that boy's chicken."
She say, "You shouldn't have killed him."
She said, "I didn't know."
So they give me six bidies and I say, "I don't want no six bidies,
I want my chicken back."
So what got me so hooked onto this bird, I say, "One of these days,
I'm gonna get me one of those birds."
♪ [Cell phone ringtone] ♪
Oh, sorry.
- Okay.
I definitely, I definitely gonna get it.
All right, Tommy.
Page 6?
Oh, okay, Tommy.
Okay, Tommy.
And see, I owe so much.
You guys are -- oh, Tommy.
I'll see you.
You and your bad self.
All right, Tommy.
Tommy said they got me in The Post on page six.
Oh Lord, have mercy.
What can I say?
♪[music starts playing]♪
You got The,The Post?
You got The Post?
Oh. They don't have The Post.
[Speaking/greeting neighbors]
Ah! Shoot.
Oh! My God.
[Charles Bradley laughing]
Yes! Oh! My God.
Look at this.
Shoot. They got me in the paper.
- Oh my goodness.
- Oh, man what are you doing?
- [Charles] That's me right there.
I thank God for this. Oh! My God!
- This guy has been, he's been doing a lot of struggling within itself,
but he's gonna be okay today, he's gonna be okay.
We, we've been talking for years.
And I look at him and I say to myself,
"He's gonna be there after he prays."
- He in the paper?
- Yeah.
- He's in the paper?
- I'm sitting here talking and you in the paper?
- Yeah, right there.
- My lord.
I'm about to hurt you, you coulda knocked on my door and told me that.
-I just found out not too long ago myself.
- I told you, I told you, baby.
You know I love you.
- You told me.
- I told you.
- It's happening.
- I told you, keep the faith and never stop believing that you're already there.
What are you worry about?
You've been there and it's already done.
- Congratulations.
-[neighbor] God has been good.
And if you cry, it's a good crywhen you do hold you head up.
because he has you still.
- I love you brother and I won't forget.
♪ [music starts palying] ♪
Tonight is my first night, me only on stage, Charles Bradley.
My chance has finally come and I'm hoping everybody out there
will come out to show me their support.
This is one of my best friends.
- You all right?
- You're coming tonight.
You know you, you always tell me you are gonna come in our show.
This is the place where before they fixed it up,
I lived in here for about, God,about two and a half years.
It was abandoned and it now it's a church.
The guy that owned it sold it, and they fixed it up.
Well that's, that's, that, this was home one time,
and this guy Jose, he is the one that really gave me
electricity from his place, kept me going.
That's why we're so close friends today.
♪ [music playing] ♪
Tonight is the night that I truly find, do I keep going?
Do I have it?
That's what I'm looking for.
You like rhythm and blues?
- Do I?
- Please come and join tonight.- [female passer-by] Alright.
-[Charles] I'm gonna be doing some good music for you.
- And I hope I can make you feel some good memories.
- Okay. Thank you so much.
- What's your name?
- Andrea.
- My sister name Andrea Laura.
- Look at that.
- Oh.
- What, what's her middle name?
- it is Andrea Laura Bradley.
- I'm Andrea Lauren. Shut up.
- See there. We're meant to meet.
- Yeah. And I love purple.
- Oh! My God.
- This is a good day.
- God bless you, sweetheart.
I've been struggling for my music over 47 years and hoping
that this will be the thing for me.
I hope this is my chance to present thisto the world and hope the world likes it.
- Most people could have just given upand you know, not done anything.
Just settle into a job.
And, you know, he's just been plugging away doing music.
- It's hard enough for people in their 30s to launch a career.
Someone in their 60s, it's almost insane.
- Excellent. Sounds good.
- You guys like rhythm and blues?
- We already got our tickets.- We're going.
-Ah, c'mon.
[clapping sound]
♪ [music continues to play]♪
[Charles] I'm gonna see if I can findsomething to, um, add to my jumpsuit,
and spice it up a little bit for my album release.
That is beautiful, that is beautiful too, that's really...
- Thank you, boss.
- Okay, boss.
- Have a good day.
- Thank you.
- What I do when I see something thatI like
and it costs a lot of money and I can't afford it
and I see something in a second-hand thrift store that I like,
I say, "That material is nice."
So I get that, and then I find two and two together, put it together.
And maybe it's not look like
but it's gonna give me the same quality I'm looking for.
That piece on the back of it, is a piece of .
This piece right here, this is the piece that I just bought me a t-shirt,
cut it out, put it back there just to make it look different.
I'm sewing on a collar.
It's like a hand, hand collar to give it a little pizazz
And Ill get time to put it on the, on the legs.
- [Tommy] I just hope it's a decent nightsome people turn out,
and you know he's got a room to performto and feels good about the record
'cause we feel good about it.
[subway train running]
[honking/traffic sound]
- Wow, wow, sold out.
My God...
- [announcer] That's right I am talking about.
No time for dreaming, please welcome
for the goodness' sake, Mr. Charles Bradley.
- Put it this way, I was in the guest list and working for the label.
And friends that play in the band and I had to wait outside like,
I don't know, 25 minutes beforeI could even get in the door.
It was sold out.
♪ [band playing] ♪
[audience cheering]
Ladies and gentlemans, I've got a special lady in the house.
I think it's Momma.
My Momma's in the house someplace.
[audience cheering]
Momma.
Look around in the, in the, in the rear over there.
I think that's my Momma over there.
But ladies and gentlemans, she gave me the start.
♪ [band start playing] ♪
♪ Ohhh...♪
♪ Go back ♪
♪ Go back to the golden rule ♪
♪[back-up singers] Golden rule...♪
♪ Go back ♪
♪ Go back to the golden rule ♪
♪[back-up singers] Golden rule...♪
You know, let me say a few words right now.
You. You, you made me to be the person I am.
Thank you. Thank you.
I thank you and I hope to God that I cankeep giving you love, decency and honesty.
♪ [music playing] ♪
♪Owww...♪
♪ What I'm gonna do?♪
♪ What I'm gonna say?♪
♪ Owww...♪
[audience applauding]
What love can I ask for around me right now?
Tell me God ain't real.
With this love that I feel around me,
will make me reach in my heart
and give everybody a little piece that say, "I love you."
- It's one of my special shows of the year.
It changed my life. Changed my life.
- It's infectious.
You know, he's just in love with what he's doing.
He's in love with his audience.
How can you not enjoy it?
- When he says I love you guys, you feel it.
- Amazing.
I brought my friend from Italy and he, what do you think?
- [Charles] I think it was too small a place
for the people that came there.
'Cause a lot of people was turned down and it hurted me to see that.
But for the joy, the love that peoples gave me, that was them.
Oh! My God!
They wanted more from me.
And I felt that I look in the traces of their faces,
Oh my, oh my God, it was a tear-dropper...
♪ [The World (Is Going Up In Flames) ] ♪
Lord! have mercy.
Wah!
- I knew the record was gonna doreal well, but I didn't know how quickly.
People don't really know him that well
and it's sales for a guy that's just putting out his first LP,
that not too many people know about.
I mean, it's unbelievable.
♪ [music continues to play] ♪
- We're like, really against the odds to be able to think that,
yes, a 62 year old black man from Woodstock, Brooklyn,
is gonna have his first record
and within the first couple of weeks, sell more than most records
are selling in a year, at this point.
♪ [music continues to play] ♪
- I don't think it's a done deal.
I don't think it's easy.
I think a lot more people are gonna buy his record.
He's gonna sing a lot more shows.
He's gonna make a lot more records.
You know, it's a long, it's a long path, you know.
And he's a late starter.
- It's above any of our expectationsalready, I think the record's got wheels.
I don't think it's stopping now.
I don't think we have seenthe biggest sales yet.
Ahhh!
- Lord have mercy.
- Yeah.
- Oh, God!
- We're leaving to go to Europe to do some touring over there and I hope that
the real Europe will love what I'm doing, what I'm giving to them.
Now, it's clean as a baby's tail.
- So, how long you be gone, baby?
- Three weeks, Momma.
- Three weeks, baby?
- Yeah.
- Oh, I'm gonna miss you, son.
- Uh-uh. You live right here.
Every three days, I'm gonna call you.
- Okay, darling.
- I'm a bad boy.
You ain't got no water to throw on me now.
You ain't got no water. I can tickle you.
I can tickle you now.
♪ [music starts palying] ♪
And like, my mom said today,
she never believed that I would, I would get this level.
I wanna see how far canI make myself go in life.
See can I go further than any of my family members ever been.
And say, I took me there.
You all peoples out there, watch out.
An old man's coming up before you, and I'd do your job better.
If you don't, I'm gonna do it for you.
- Do you want to work on that song from last week?
- Which one?
- I Thank You.
♪ [I Thank You playing] ♪
- He really gettin' the really nitty gritty.
♪ [I Thank You continues playing] ♪
Ahh!
So, that's the way I am.
Woo.
♪ [I Thank You continues playing] ♪
- 'Cause when I leave this world, this world owe me nothing.
- Well, gimme back my dollar now.
- Get off me.
- Man, gimme back my dollar.
♪ [I Thank You continues playing] ♪
- Oh, my passport, wait a minute.
- Save your lobster every now.
- Jimmy, you don't eat lobster, you always give it to me.
- I'll start eating tonight.
♪ [I Thank You continues playing] ♪
- You sure said fast, that's my quarter. I saw it.
- I picked it up.
♪ [I Thank You continues playing] ♪